## **Matt Niederhuber**



Genomics | Lasers | Wings

#### Contact

- 0
- 0
- 0
- 0
- 0

#### Skills

#### Computational:

NGS data processing, NGS data exploration and analysis, HPC, Unix CLI, Pipeline customization, Snakemake, Git, ImageJ, Adobe Creative Suite

#### Programming:

R, Python, Bash, HTML

### Wet Lab:

Molecular techniques, Microscopy, NGS library prep, FAIRE-seq, CUT&RUN, Cell culture, Cloning I am a developmental and computational biologist with strong experience in generating and analyzing large NGS datasets. I'm passionate about communicating science through writing and by obsessing over data visualization.

## **Experience**

#### **Doctoral Candidate**

August 2016 - August 2023

Advisor: Dr. Daniel J. McKay University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill NC

- > Led two projects on the regulation of enhancer activity in *Drosophila* wing development that resulted in first-author publications
- > Hands-on experience performing NGS assays like FAIRE-seq and CUT&RUN, generating NGS libraries, and performing library QC
- > Experience writing custom code in Python, R, and Bash to process raw NGS data, manage pipelines, analyze high-dimensional data, and generate publication quality graphics

#### Research Assistant II

June 2014 - July 2016

PI: Dr. Pamela A. Silver

Harvard Medical School, Boston MA

> Led a project that studied the 3-D structure of the Cyanobacterial carboxysome using super-resolution microscopy that resulted in a firstauthor publication

## Research Assistant

PI: Dr. Jerard Hurwitz

June 2013 - June 2014 MSKCC, New York NY

## **Education**

PhD - Genetics & Molecular Biology	2016 - 2023
University of North Carolina	Chapel Hill, NC
> NSF Graduate Research Fellow	

# Certificate - Premedical Sciences

Columbia University

2011 - 2013 New York NY

BA - English Literature Kenyon College **2006 - 2010** *Gambier, OH* 

# **Selected Publications**

#### Academic:

**Niederhuber MJ**, Leatham-Jensen M, McKay DJ. 2023. The SWI-SNF nucleosome remodeler constrains enhancer activity during *Drosophila* wing development. bioRxiv. DOI: 10.1101/2023.07.17.549384

**Niederhuber MJ**, McKay DJ. 2021. Mechanisms underlying the control of dynamic regulatory element activity and chromatin accessibility during metamorphosis. COIS. DOI: 10.1016/j.cois.2020.08.007

Nystrom SL\*, **Niederhuber MJ\***, McKay DJ. 2020. Expression of E93 provides an instructive cue to control dynamic enhancer activity and chromatin accessibility during development. Development. DOI: 10.1242/dev.181909 \*equal contributors

#### Popular:

"UNC Scientists Partner with Citizen Scientists to Map Earth's River Obstructions." UNC Institute for the Environment, 2019.

"Making Time Matter: How Hormone Pulses Direct Chromatin Accessibility During Development." Development: The Node, 2017.

"Yes, This Exists: A Biohacker Hotline" Popular Science, 2013.